Well I am a trained relativistic astrophysicist and I got my PhDs always in physics departments
working on astrophysics problems involving general relativity, gas dynamics and so forth
and so in the 70s when I was developing what is now called numerical general relativity
which is the way to solve Einstein's equations for dynamics of black holes, colliding black
holes or in astrophysics that require general relativity like supernova events and so on.
I had to go and get a top secret nuclear weapons clearance to get access to supercomputers
because in the mid 70s the only place to get a supercomputer was either at Livermore in
Los Alamos or in one area which was weather. Now astronomy has always been a driver of
supercomputing and in fact on Johnny von Neumann's computer that was built by the Institute half
of that went to army to Aberdeen. Half of that was used of course for the army for trajectory
calculations but the other half was used for stellar evolution. So astronomy and von Neumann's
interest in weather meant that astronomy and weather for 50 years basically have been dominant
drivers of supercomputing usage and yet to do pure astrophysics you're having to get
a top secret nuclear weapons clearance. Now nobody seemed to think there was anything
unusual about this and so I just went ahead as a post doc and I would get a few months
in the summer, work a hundred hours a week and then the last of the year I'd have to
live off that, go back to Harvard where I was a junior fellow, try to explain to them
about one could solve the laws of physics that we had been laying down for 300 years
in incredible detail for engineering devices like nuclear weapons that put on earth temperatures
of the center of the sun, stresses beyond anything that we could imagine in academic
problems that we were trying to solve in lots of disciplines. So this thing could revolutionize
academic research. Well nobody got it. I really felt like I was transitioning in a flying
saucer between this advanced civilization at Livermore and this Stone Age culture at
Harvard and Harvard was as advanced as any place in thinking about this. I didn't figure
this out until it was in the early 80s and by then the first Cray had gone into the continent
of Europe in an open scientific institute, the Max Planck Institute of Physics and Astrophysics
so I'm over there in the summer along with people like Dave Arnett who is one of the
great supernova super computer guys in our country and people in chemistry and it was
like Paris in the 20s with all these ex-patriots sitting over there and we're like trying to
figure this out like it's an American built super computer right? Why are we in Munich?
Right? I mean this is very strange. So but you know in America we don't question the
infrastructure somehow. I mean it's just like it's either there or it isn't there or that's
just the way it is. But I was having a mass of beer late one night. Actually I think it
was the second mass of beer with my German host who had also been born like I was post
war and he finally turns to me and he says aren't you ashamed of yourself? You big rich
occupying country. You come over here in our little country and we finally get enough money
scraped together after World War II to buy one of these super computers and you Americans
come over here and use up our time. He says how did you guys ever win the war? What is
going on here? And so this finally sort of just stimulated me into saying what is going
on here? This is nuts and I went back and I found out for instance that after the Sputnik
program the federal government had funded the universities, built the science buildings,
converted the super computer centers, IBM would go around and give away almost the main
frames and so the scientists in the 60s took it for granted that they had the fastest computers
in the world in academia. But about 1970 with the starting of the Vietnam War and with all
kinds of guns and butters issues and everything else that stopped. And in fact to give you
an example by 78 half the number of PhDs and engineers in engineering was being generated
in our country as there were in 1970. So there was this complete severing of the Sputnik
era partnership with the federal government and it was particularly bad in computing.
To give you an example when I was at Livermore in the 70s there were four CDC 7600s which
were just one of the finest super computers ever built. No American university ever took
delivery of a single CDC 7600. In fact the University of Illinois when I first got here
had a cyber 175 which was a retread, a second design manufacturing of this thing and we
were one of the first universities that had it and people all thought that Illinois naturally
was way ahead of everybody else. So it's like we were just completely divorced from the
private sector that was generating these wonderful machines because of federal policy which was
to say these things are so valuable that we can only afford to put them into war environments.
So after this German encounter I came back and I said well gee I wonder how many other
scientists like me are there. So at the University of Illinois I started cold calling my colleagues
and saying hi you don't know me I'm a little assistant professor but I bet you that your
research is blocked by lack of access to super computers and they sort of said like who is
this you know crank call and but we'd start talking in chemistry and biology and agriculture
and so on and sure enough it turns out that that was true they knew how to do the science
they just didn't have access. So I said well send me a little perspective of what science
you could do if you had a super computer. Well I ended up with 65 faculty in 15 departments
on one campus and I thought this has got to be this way all over the country. So it was
I really said saying well gee somebody's got to raise this issue and about that time there
had been a lax report that had the federal government had done to begin to undercover
some of this stuff but they still weren't I remember Peter lax he was one of the greatest
mathematicians head of one of the top people in the cron institute a long time advocate
of things computational and I had this long long battle with Peter because in the draft
report of the lax report it was not it was going to say well yeah we got to get one of
these super computers and make it available to the universities but you know let's put
it at Livermore put it somewhere that people know how to do this stuff and a university
was not on the list of what the lax report considered to be appropriate sites for a supercomputer
so I had this long battle over the telephone I remember with Peter lax sort of David and
Goliath because I mean he was this giant of the field I'm nobody and I finally convinced
him not to exclude universities as a possibility even though he felt that it was fairly unlikely
that any of them would be able to play with sharp instruments and not hurt themselves
so I mean you gotta understand the world was totally different when the supercomputer centers
program was coming into being and people it's so hard for people now on the web and everything
to go back to that time there was no internet you know there was there was these wonderful
people vent surf and bob con and all these people bill joy who had developed tcpip and
embodied it in the arpanet this is a few computer science departments and military okay nobody
in a physics department or chemistry department ever heard of the arpanet much less had any
access to it but it was obviously the right idea and so once we got the congress to put
through money for a national supercomputer program then there was a national competition
and and and so on and the five centers were selected the first thing then that NSF realized
well okay now we put these in place to be providing access to academic scientists and
yet like they have to fly to champaign urbana like I had to fly to livermore okay this isn't
right so there were a lot of discussions then but the trouble was that the telecom lobbyist
in washington would block any discussion of the federal government putting in the kind
of network we have today which is what people wanted I mean everybody knew that they wanted
to have a ubiquitous email person to person network but as soon as they'd start talking
about that the telecom lobbyist would come up and say no way guys that's private sector
don't get the federal government involved in that stay out of it so what we learned
early on is real interesting it's like if we had argued instead of the supercomputer
program let's get the federal government to buy everybody a personal computer which was
IBM personal computer was two years old in 1985 and put on people's desk okay again this
would be an interference with the private sector so but we said oh we'll just take a few of
these esoteric supercomputers and they said okay that's right there's no market there
that's okay the federal government has a role well it was the same thing with networking
what we said is we just want to put a high speed backbone across the country to connect
the five centers and the telecom people said okay that's cool you know 56 kilobits was
the national high speed backbone less than ISDN today yeah that's not a market okay and
we said we got a few of these weird supercomputer types who are out in universities who want
to hook into that they say yeah that's okay that's not a market you can do that well that
was the NSF net backbone then the regionals got funded and then the campuses were afraid
that if they didn't dig up their quad and put in some fiber then the professors who
wanted to get access to supercomputers would go to a university that would do that so gradually
the whole internet emerged out of the sort of policy vice you get into Washington where
you can't do the right thing you have to do something that seems irrelevant but has a
logic to it that will gradually bring the market forces into play that will spin out
ultimately a whole industry.